<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands glory by the benefit of wool manufactured therin, from the farmer to the merchant : and the evil consequences of its exportation unmanufactured : briefly hinted, with submission to better judgments.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11638</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13301699</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13301699</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98929</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38392)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98929)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 453:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands glory by the benefit of wool manufactured therin, from the farmer to the merchant : and the evil consequences of its exportation unmanufactured : briefly hinted, with submission to better judgments.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p., [2], 11-34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. M. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wool industry --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:98929:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98929:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Englands Glory.</head>
            <head type="sub">BY THE Benefit of <hi>Wool</hi> Manufactured therein, from the <hi>Farmer</hi> to the <hi>Merchant;</hi> and the <hi>Evil</hi> Conſequences of its Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Unmanufactured. <hi>Briefly Hinted,</hi> With Submiſſion to better Judgments.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no King nor Prince in the World, known by experience, or upon Record, that hath ſuch means to ſupport their Splendour and Greatneſs as his Majeſty of great <hi>Britain,</hi> nor has any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or Nation ſuch variety of ſtaple Commodities within it ſelf, and in ſuch abundance, as hath the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> which are ſaid by ſome to be a Hundred Native Commodities, which produceth a Thouſand ſorts of Manufactures: So that if thoſe advantages were duly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98929:2"/>
               <hi>England</hi> might be a general Mart for the whole World, and then by conſequence be the glory thereof. That thoſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are not improved is too too obvious to all that look into it, by the ſore complaints that are frequently made of the great proverty and decay thereof; and indeed (which is worſt of all) by that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral deſperation of ſpirit which will not put forth a hand to help, ſupport, or prevent the total deſolation of our Country, upon a prepoſſeſt opinion, that all endeavours will be rendred fruitleſs and abortive.</p>
            <p>The conſideration whereof hath greatly prompted me (who muſt confeſs my ſelf the meaneſt of Thouſands more concerned) to uſe the utmoſt of my little ſkill, and unwearied diligence (though but as the Womans mite) to the right management of ſo great an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking; that the threatned ruine of all may be prevented, and (of poſſible) ſome good part of what is loſt may be recovered. And whereas many have taken in hand to ſet forth theſe things, ſome treating of one thing, and other of another, which if all was collected and harmonized, it might very much conduce to the promoting of this weighty affair, of ſo publick a value: I ſhall confine my ſelf to thoſe things only, whereof I have had not only credible information, but a conſiderable (though a ſad) experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal knowledge; and in a more particular and eſpecial manner that of <hi>Wool,</hi> and of its Manufacture and Conſequences; which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many, is the Richeſt Treaſure in his Majeſties Dominions, the flower, ſtrength, and ſinews of this Nation; a Land uniting the People into Societies, for their own Utility; it is the Milk and Honey to the Grazier and Country Farmer; the Gold and Spices of the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies</hi> to the Merchant, and Citizens, the continued ſupply of Bread to the Poor: and in a word, the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer of wealth, and ſtaple of protection to the whole, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and at home; and therefore of full merit to be had in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual remembrance, defence, and encouragement for the moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous improvement thereof.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Wools</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (before it was manufactured within it ſelf) have ever been of great account and eſteem abroad, ſufficiently teſtified unto, by the great amity, which it begat, and for many Hundred Years (inviolably) maintained, between the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and Dukes of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> only for the great benefit, that (from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98929:2"/>that Commodity) did accrew to that People, inſomuch that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wools, they receiv'd at 6 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound, they returned again (through their induſtrious manufacture thereof) in Cloth, at 10 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard, to the great inriching of that State, both in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Revenues of their Soveraign, and in a full em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment (thereby) continued among the People; whereby the Merchants of this Nation were occaſioned, (as a People unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be wholly diſpriviledged of ſo great a benefit) to tranſport themſelves (with their Families (in great numbers) into <hi>Flanders,</hi> from whence they held a conſtant Commerce with moſt parts of the World; this continued without intermiſſion, between <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Burgundy,</hi> until King <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d. made his mighty Conqueſts over <hi>France,</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland,</hi> and as a ſuitable improvement of ſo great a mercy, did wiſely project, and alſo accompliſh the manufacture of Wools within the Bowels of this Kingdom, to the great inriching of his own People, and alſo to the Peopling of his new Conquered Dominions; the memory of whoſe wiſdome and care for his People, is worthy to be had in remembrance by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, unto the Worlds end.</p>
            <p>The ſaid King having thus ſetled the manufacture of Wools within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> confined it by a penal Statute, which (at firſt) reached not only to Goods, Chattels, and Land, but alſo to Members, and Life it ſelf; but in a ſhort time repealed the two latter thereof, continuing the other in its full force to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main to future Generations: which exceeding great advantage to the proſperity of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Trade, hath now continued theſe Three Hundred Years, by the vigilancy of the Kingdoms Monarchs, and the protection of its Laws, in the continued careful execution thereof upon offenders, with more than a little diligence to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt the thirſting deſires of Foreiners to wreſt this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive priviledge (of ſo great a moment) out of <hi>Engliſh</hi> hands, which by the providence of God (through the great care of our Anceſtors) has been (for many Ages) enjoyed by the Nation, as it is indeed its proper right: But ſo it is, that (for ſome years paſt) the diligence of Foreiners, to enrich themſelves upon us, has ſo much exceeded our care to preſerve our ſelves, that it's now come to, if not beyond a queſtion, Who have the greateſt benefit of the manufacture of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wools, they who have no right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, or they to whom of right it doth belong?</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98929:3"/>
            <p> That this is indeed ſo, will appear, by conſidering that not only <hi>Holland, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> have long ſucked the ſweetneſs of the ſinews of our Trade; but <hi>France</hi> is likewiſe learning to be too hard for us, as is manifeſt by the great quantities of Wools, that (of late years) have been tranſported from <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> thither; how injurious it muſt be to us, is alſo unqueſtionable, if we conſider the conſequence thereof, which was (without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) much in the Eye of our Anceſtors, as appeares by what is above hinted in <hi>Edward</hi> the 3ds time, and in ſeveral Kings Reigns ſince.</p>
            <p>Every Pack of Wool ſent to <hi>France,</hi> doth prevent us (not only) of the benefit of the manufacture thereof, but of two Packs more beſides it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> Thus, it being combing, and combed Wool (for the moſt part) exported thither, the <hi>French</hi> (having no Wools of their own, but ſuch as are very courſe) are not able to make Cloth, or fine Stuff, without the conjunction of ours therewithall; there being none (to my beſt information) fit for that purpoſe in all the World, but ours only, all other being likewiſe courſe, but <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and that much too fine (eſpecially for Worſted Stuffs, and not in any wiſe fit for combing; ſo that without <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Iriſh</hi> Wools there can be no fine Worſted Stuffs, nor a middle ſort of Cloth made, in the whole World; neither will any Wools be well mixed together, but <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> (only for Cloth) becauſe the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> is with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of one nature, being formerly <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sheep, though now much finer, from the alteration of the Climate, and the nature of the Land whereon it is fed, as by good experience appeareth here in <hi>England,</hi> both neer, and at a farther diſtance.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the exportation of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wools into <hi>France</hi> muſt of neceſſity be greatly prejudicial to this Nation, not only in the quantity ſent over, but alſo in the advantage which is thereby gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them to manufacture a double portion of their own Wool, (which formerly was little worth) into ſuch commodities, as ſpoyls us of the a vantage of our proper Trade, not only thither, but alſo into other parts, <hi>viz.</hi> in theſe three reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The combed of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wool makes Wooffe for the Warpes of the <hi>French</hi> Wool, and ſo takes up (it may be) as much as the quantity above ſpecified, to every Pack of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wool,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98929:3"/>without which, they can (only) with their Wool make Rugs, and at the beſt, Cloth for Sea-men, and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> Their combings or pinnions, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſhort Wool that's combed out of the Worſted, ſerves for their Linnen warp to make ſome of their Druggets, becauſe their Linnen being fine ſpun, and coloured, is not diſcernable to all Perſons, to be that we call <hi>Linſie Woolſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> The fineſt ſhort <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wool is mixed with the loweſt of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wool, called ſhort Wool, for ſome of their beſt Druggets, that is woove for Worſted Chanies, and alſo for a middle ſort of Broad-cloth, about 10 <hi>s.</hi> or 12 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard. This is the cauſe (I judg) that ſhort <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wool is ſo ſcarce here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if we conſider theſe things together, the dammage of the exporting of this one Pack from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> at about 10 <hi>l.</hi> or 12 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling, preventing the manufacturing of two Packs more in <hi>England,</hi> which would be worth one 100 <hi>l. Englands</hi> loſs (in the whole) by the exportation of a Pack of Wool, is little leſs than 90<hi>l.</hi> in its firſt exportation, moreover conſidering the Cuſtom paid when exported (if manufactured in <hi>England</hi>) with the Frait and Cuſtom where it is imported; the product of all theſe char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges augmenting the 100 <hi>l.</hi> when ſold there, laid out in another commodity beyond Sea, the Cuſtom whereof being paid there, with Frait and Cuſtom (when imported) in <hi>England,</hi> it's much, if it do not more than double the firſt principal.</p>
            <p>Now, if it be ſo, that the exportation of one Pack of <hi>Engliſh</hi> wool, exported at 10 <hi>l.</hi> or 12 <hi>l.</hi> be neer 200 <hi>l.</hi> dammage to the King and Kingdom in general, is the conſequence; what will be the loſs in the exporting of 10. or 15 Thouſand Packs into <hi>France</hi> (in two Years time) is eaſily accounted (by ſuch) as are concerned in the affaires: And although this evil is almoſt incredible to many, yet it is too manifeſt, to ſuch as have made (ſomething) their buſineſs to look into it; and not only ſo, but theſe further inconveniences muſt (by this means) ariſe upon us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The ſpoyling of our Trade with <hi>France</hi> in all our Woollen manufactures, as doth already appear, by the Impoſt put upon the ſame, there, from 20. to 40. <hi>per Cent.</hi> ſince ſo great quantitie of our VVools is exported thither, whereunto woful experience may be a ſufficient witneſs.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98929:4"/>
            <p> And ſecondly, In time it will capacitate the <hi>French,</hi> as well as the <hi>Dutch,</hi> (if not much better) to under-ſell our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, in Forrein Parts, nay (poſſibly) in our own Country, (to this, I ſhall only mention the words of a Merchant in <hi>Flanders,</hi> by Letter to another here, treating on this matter thus, <hi>We Engliſh have our throats cut, with our own Weapons, wondering at the stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of the Engliſh here, that they ſhould ſo long omit, to poſſeſs the King's Majeſty with this deplorable and dangerous caſe, in reſpect to the preſent and future inconveniences thereof.</hi>) by reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (as in time the <hi>French</hi> will not only prevent our <hi>Engliſh</hi> wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len manufactures, to be ſold in <hi>France</hi> (as before minded) and alſo in other Forrein Parts, but alſo bring theirs into <hi>England,</hi> and ſell them for four times the value here, to the great inriching of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to the impoveriſhing of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> only by new fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick ſopperies; for which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> pay not leſs than ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſands in a year, to get themſelves into the <hi>French</hi> mode. So much (indeed) have we been deceived (in this matter) to our ſhame, as well as to our apparent loſs; that whereas (in time of the late War) with the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> thoſe <hi>French</hi> Druggets were thereby much prevented, many <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtriped broad-cloths rent through into three parts (about 10 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard, price) being put into the form of <hi>French</hi> Druggets, were ſold in each part at 8 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard; and ſo (in the whole) came to 1 <hi>l.</hi> 4 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard. So likewiſe it is certainly true, that many of thoſe Druggets made here in <hi>England</hi> goe for <hi>French,</hi> and in order thereunto, directed to <hi>French</hi> Men in ſome of our Southern parts, have from thence been conveighed unto <hi>London</hi> (and there ſold for <hi>French</hi> Goods) to have coloured the buſineſs with the Cuſtom-houſe Officers, to ſave the Cuſtom of <hi>French</hi> Druggets. And this continued long, before the cheat could be diſcovered; but being once found out by the Clothier, (who could not (to his own private advantage) conceal ſuch an apparent injury to his Country, it was ſoon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented: whereby we may come to ſee (with clearneſs) the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that that People makes upon our <hi>Engliſh</hi> fanſies, by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling us in the ſame kind of commodities, that they make out of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wools, joyned (as before minded) with their own; having alſo an advantage thereunto, by the cheapneſs of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures thereof, beyond what we can do (the <hi>French</hi> being
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98929:4"/>very populous, and living harder than we can in <hi>England;</hi> as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by their Linnens, that Paying Fraight and Cuſtom with profit to the Merchant, yet can be afforded cheaper than can be made in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſo it is, that the advantage we give them, beſides, in the mixture of our Wools with theirs, is ſuch, that whereas their Wool of it ſelf, is not worth above 4 <hi>l. per</hi> Pack, being mixed with ours, becomes ſo fit for Worſted Stuffes, as that it comes to be worth no leſs than 12 <hi>l. per</hi> Pack. So that all thoſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, it becomes obvious to every Eye, (that doth not (wilfully) cloſe it ſelf) that the exportation of Wool from <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is of a dangerous and deſtructive nature to the very being of the Trade of this Kingdom. Whatever objections have been made (with reſpect to the Graziers preſent advantage) thereunto, whoſe loſs may poſſibly be ſuppoſed (by prohibiting exportation) to be about 20 <hi>s.</hi> in every Pack of Wool that's ſo exported: In anſwer whereunto, I have this to ſay, That though it may be granted, it will be ſo for a time in this one particular commodity, yet ſuch will (thereby) be the ſpoyl of the general Trade of the Nation, that what is gotten in one, will be loſt in every other commodity, as Corn, Beefs, and Muttons; on each of which, with the Wools, the Farmers and Graziers advantage doth much more than equally depend; beſides the inevitable danger of the ruine of our Trade, and ſo conſequently the ſtarving of our Poor, without ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary means for their ſupport; who while the priviledge of our Trade is kept inviolate with other Nations, we have money plentifully to expend for the advancement of the Farmers and the Graziers; for that is that which chiefly advanceth the Grazier and Farmer, which is Fleſh and Corn, and not the quantity of Wool, as afterwards will more fully appear.</p>
            <p>And it hath always been obſerved (in former and latter times) hitherto, that when the Clothiers have had the beſt Trade at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> the Farmer did not looſe his ſhare in the advantage thereof in the Country; according to the diſpoſe of providence, who hath ordered Nations, but more eſpecially the People of every Nation, (in matters of this kind) to depend upon each other, and ſo to riſe or fall together, as they are deſigned to mercy, or to judgment, by the hand of God. Theſe things conſidered, with a little delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98929:5"/>it will manifeſtly appear, that the exporting of our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Wool, will not only prove the ſpoyl of our Merchants and Clothiers Trade, and ſo conſequently expoſe the Poor to deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſtraits for ſubſiſtence, but (in ſhort time) muſt of neceſſity make the Country-mens imployments (of every kind) to come to little, and ſo make them uncapable of paying Rent.</p>
            <p>For, if it be ſo, that while we have but a little Trade, we can hardly live one by another, What may be expected, if our Trade ſhould be taken away? which is now more in danger (by the <hi>French</hi>) than it hath been theſe 300. Years paſt— And then we may conſider, what the price of Wool may be in <hi>England,</hi> when we by our remiſneſs ſhall loſe our Trade, by the skill and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting practices of Foreiners, and we helping forwards for a ſuppoſed profit; For there was not more art and skill in our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, to bring home the work at firſt to the Wool, and prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting the exportation thereof, and ſetling the manufacturing in <hi>England,</hi> than is now to export the materials thereof unmanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factured. The neceſſary conſequence will be to bring the Price of Wool (as it was 300. Years agon, when moſt was exported) to 6 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound, as appears in a little Piece, called, <hi>The Golden Fleece,</hi> written by <hi>W. S.</hi> Gent.) in the Year, 56. although the Cloth made in <hi>Flanders</hi> of our Wools, at 6 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound, was then ſold here in <hi>England</hi> at 10 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard, when at this Day the Cloth made in <hi>England</hi> of Wool, worth 12 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yield 7 <hi>s. per</hi> Yard, which is above 30. <hi>per Cent.</hi> worſe to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Trade now, than it was to the <hi>Flemmings</hi> formerly.</p>
            <p>And though for the preſent, the price of Wool be riſen by its exportation, yet if the quantity lately exported (being no leſs than 20. Thouſand Packs) had been kept in <hi>England,</hi> the quantity (if not with 10. Thouſand Packs more) would in time have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in the particular manufactures. For if the Wool was not exported to thoſe places beyond the Seas, there to be manufactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they muſt of neceſſity have our Woollen manufacture, and then could not have thoſe advantages (as before hinted) by our Wools, to improve the <hi>French</hi> wool, and ſhort <hi>Spaniſh</hi> wool, and their fine-ſpun Linnens.</p>
            <p>By all which, it is ſo obvious, that in time to come, the VVools in <hi>England</hi> would be much cheaper, becauſe by the aforeſaid
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98929:5"/>means, leſs Wool would be uſed in <hi>England;</hi> and beſides that which would be uſed, the manufacture would be ſo low, that it could not bear up any price (as is begun already in <hi>France,</hi> and will ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow in <hi>England</hi>) for it is generally reported, that Wool is as cheap in <hi>France</hi> at this Day, as it is in ſome parts where it is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>England.</hi> And if it be ſo now, what in reaſon can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, as the effects of theſe two things? <hi>viz.</hi> The firſt, when the great quantity that is lately exported to <hi>France,</hi> with thoſe three additions before hinted, that the 20. Thouſand Packs helps to work out, and eſpecially moſt making VVorſted Stuffs, which goes as far by that means, as 40. Thouſand Packs of Wool would if uſed in <hi>England,</hi> becauſe it would be made more into ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Cloaths, which conſumes more Wool, than thoſe light and thin Stuffes do: which is a ſufficient Anſwer to that Objection, that the great quantity of any commodity, that is exported, muſt be of ſcarcity, and ſo conſequently raiſe the price: which I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, if it was a conſumptive commodity, but it is quite contrary in this. For as our experience is, when the VVool was all uſed in <hi>England,</hi> (or very little exported) then it was 18 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound, and when all, or the greateſt part was exported, it was at 6 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound.</p>
            <p>The wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>What is, hath been;</hi> and, <hi>what hath been, may be again;</hi> and ſo no new thing.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with a ſhort review of the Graziers and Farm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, preſent loſs: In the greateſt Commodity, which pays his Rent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was formerly hinted. Suppoſe, through want of Trade, Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton be ſold but at 6 <hi>d. per</hi> Quarter (which is but little) being 2 <hi>s. per</hi> Sheep; and there being ſome Sheep that one 100. will but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Pack of Wool (though ſome leſs) that comes to 10 <hi>l.</hi> which is the worth of the Pack of Wool, (and ſo proportionably as to Beefs) which is wholly loſt to the Grazier.</p>
            <p>And for the Corn (as I ſuppoſe) there may be about 50 <hi>ls.</hi> worth, (as far as I can judge in my travels, to One Hundred S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>p throughout the Nation, which for want of a Trade, it may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (at ſome ſeaſons) come to Thirty or Forty at moſt; and if a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Trade, it may be worth Sixty or Seventy: By which means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eaſily be demonſtrated, how the Farmers come to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>povriſhed.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98929:6"/>
            <p> The advantage of the Tenant conſiſts in the advance of the greateſt Commodity that pays his Rent, which is not in Wool, but in Corn: and it is a neceſſary conſequence; that there being ſo many Thouſand Families depending upon the Cloathing Trade, which (as before hinted) was inſtrumental to advance the price of Corn, that where-ever Trade is, there People are moſt populous, and when thoſe Perſons are deprived of their Trade, depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly upon it, they muſt unavoidably come to the Pariſhes: which is in many Places begun already, and Daily increaſing; and feared in time will ſo increaſe, that the Poor will be expecting more than there will be to contribute to them. And as there be in many Country Pariſhes Ten that live on the Trade, for One that can live of himſelf. VVhat will become of thoſe Pariſhes, when the Trade is gone? So that it may eaſily be concluded that the Farmers loſs for want of Trade is four-fold greater than the Pack of VVool, by the lowneſs of the price of Corn. And this is the true reaſon: for thoſe Perſons that formerly, when there was a Trade, could lay out <hi>Ten Shillings</hi> in Corn, have now but <hi>Five Shillings,</hi> which being multiplyed by Hundreds of Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in the Nation, it will be no difficult point to ſee which way the Grazier and Farmer come to be undone, and ſo are forced to give up their Lands into their Landlords hands: For it is not ſo much the ſuper-abounding Crops that leſſens the price of Corn, but the want of Money. For I have known as much Corn grow Yearly, formerly, as is now, (when Trade was good) to be 20. or 30. <hi>per Cent.</hi> dearer than now.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:98929:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> in the Year 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:98929:7"/>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98929:7"/>
            <p>SInce the foregoing papers were printed, I met with an Objection againſt what was aſſerted page the 4th. <hi>(viz.)</hi> The <hi>French</hi> having that advantage of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wool, to help work up theirs being worſer; and likewiſe, that according to my beſt Information, there was none fit for ſuch purpoſes in all the world, <hi>(viz.)</hi> for fine Worſteds, or a middle ſort of Cloath, but <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> (which is all one;) The Objection were, that there was Wools in moſt parts of the world; therefore why not proper for thoſe purpoſes? Anſwer, that there is Wools was never gainſaid, but that there is ſuch Wool for fineneſs and ſubſtance in all the world, except <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> I cannot as yet ever receive, (as before I hinted) any ſatisfactory accompt. For the better ſatisfaction of the Reader, I ſhall give ſome account of the natures of Wools in <hi>England,</hi> but firſt of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wools: They are the fineſt in all the world for Cloath, but not ſo fit for Worſted, being too fine and ſhort, and thoſe Wools alſo are one in nature with our <hi>Engliſh,</hi> being at firſt from Sheep that were <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſported thither; and though that be much finer by reaſon of the Climate, yet is it ſtill one in nature; next to it is <hi>Lempſter</hi> Wool, almoſt as fine as <hi>Spaniſh;</hi> then next part of <hi>Shropſhire</hi> and <hi>Stafford-ſhire,</hi> part of <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire, Wilts, Dorſet, Hampſhire,</hi> part of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> and part of <hi>Kent, Summerſet, Devon,</hi> and <hi>Cornwall,</hi> moſt part for Cloath, ſome ſmall parts for Worſteds. Amongſt all theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, there is 9. <hi>d. per</hi> pound difference in the priſes of one place, <hi>(viz.) Lempſter,</hi> from ſome other parts; but then again part of <hi>Suſſex</hi> and <hi>Surrey, Middleſex, Hertfordſhire,</hi> and ſome other Counties 2. <hi>d.</hi> 3. <hi>d. per</hi> pound cheaper then the loweſt of the abovementioned Counties; but then for <hi>Barkeſhire, Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Warwick, Oxford, Leiceſter, Nottingham, Northampton,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98929:8"/>and <hi>Lincoln,</hi> part of <hi>Kent</hi> called <hi>Rumney Marſh,</hi> moſt part of the laſt mentioned Counties, and part of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Wools is ſo proper for Worſted Stuffs, that all the world cannot be compared with it. And hence it is, that the cares of our Anceſtors have been ſuch, (ever ſince King <hi>Edward</hi> the 3 d. in moſt Kings Reignes) there have been ſome Lawes made or altered, and in ſome Kings Reigns altered three or four times to make it effectual: and for a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial to future Generations, are the Wool-packs in the Lords Houſe in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for Seats, to put them in mind of what is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Riches of the Kingdome, that it is by the various ſtreams of the Manufactures thereof, as formerly in the Front briefly hinted from the farmer to the Merchant. I ſhall now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to give ſome particular account how all are conſerved; And before I do this, give me leave to inſert the Obſervation of a worthy Author Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> that I have met withal ſince the former Papers were Written, who ſaith, That, then which was in King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, about fourſcore thouſand undreſt &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed Cloaths yearly were Tranſported: whereby it was evident that the Kingdome hath been yearly deprived of about 400000. l. which in fifty five years is near 20 Millions, that would have been gained by the labour of poor Workmen in that time, with the Merchants gains for bringing in dying Stuffs, and returns of Cloaths dreſt and dyed, with other benefits to the Realm, beſides exceeding inlargeing of Traffick, and increaſe of Ships and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners.</p>
            <p>There would have been gained in that time, about three Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by increaſe of Cuſtoms upon Commodities returned for Cloaths dreſt and dyed, and for dying Stuffs which would have been more plentifully brought in and uſed for the ſame.</p>
            <p>There hath been alſo Tranſported in that time yearly, by Bayes, <hi>Northern</hi> and <hi>Devonſhire</hi> Kerzyes white, about 50000. Cloaths counting three Kerſyes to a Cloath, whereby hath been loſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout five Millions by thoſe ſorts of Cloaths, in that time which would have come to poor Work-men for their labour, with Cuſtoms for dying Stuffs, and the peoples proſit for bringing them in with returns of other Commodities and Fraights for ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
            <p>Bayes are Tranſported white into <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and being there
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98929:8"/>dyed and dreſt, are ſhipped into <hi>Spain, Portugal,</hi> and other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, where they are ſold in the name of <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Bayes, ſetting their own Town Seals upon them; ſo that we loſe the very name of our home-bred Commodities, and other Countrys get the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and Credit thereof. Lamentable it is that this Land ſhould be deprived of ſo many above-mentioned Millions, as that our Native Commodities of Cloath, ordained of God for the natural Subjects, being ſo Royal and rich in it ſelf, ſhould be driven to ſo ſmall advantage of Reputation &amp; Profit to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and People, and ſo much improved and intercepted by Strangers; conſidering that God hath enabled and given your Majeſty power to advance dreſſing and dying, and Tranſporting all your Cloaths within a year or two: I ſpeak it knowingly, to ſhew how it may be done laudibly, lawfully, and approved to be Honourable, feaſeable, and profitable.</p>
            <p>He obſerves alſo the increaſe of his Majeſties Cuſtoms, by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in and ſpending of dying Stuffs, as alſo ſtrength in ſhipping, &amp; ſetting ſo many thouſands of poor on work; alſo noting that in the Low-Countrys, where theſe Cloaths are dreſt and dyed, they ſtretch them to ſuch unreaſonable length, contrary to our Law, that they prevent and foreſtale our Markets, and croſs the juſt prohibition of our State and Realm, by their Agents, and Factors, lying in divers places with our own Cloaths, to the great decay of this Kingdome in general, &amp; diſcredit to our Cloaths in particular. Again, he adds, that if the accounts were truly known, it would be found that they make not clear proſit only by Cloath Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported rough, undreſt, and undyed, ſixty thouſand pounds a year; but it is moſt apparent your Majeſty, in your Cuſtoms, your Merchants in their Sales and Prizes; your Subjects in their Labours, for lack of dreſſing and dying; your Ships and Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in not bringing in of dying Stuffs, ſpending of <hi>Alum</hi> (if not <hi>Copperas</hi>) are hindered yearly near a Million of pounds: So that Trade is driven to that great hinderance of your Majeſty and People, by permitting your Native Commodities to paſs rough, undreſt, and undyed. Thus Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if it was thus with <hi>England</hi> ſo long agoe, when the Wool was ſpun and made here into ſubſtantial Cloath; and that for want only of dreſſing and dying, many Millions were loſt to the King and Kingdom: What then hath been the loſs of ſo many
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98929:9"/>thouſand Packs of Wool exported (without any improvement; eſpecially that to <hi>France,</hi> the conſequence of which is more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial (as hath been demonſtrated) than can be imagined (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting but one hundred pounds dammage by one Pack of Wool,) of which there are no leſs than ten thouſand yearly, if not much more exported, by which there is dammage a Million of pounds <hi>ſterling,</hi> yearly to this Kingdome, (beſides the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Poor for want of Imployment) out of which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties dammage cannot be leſs then 100000. pound yearly: The leſſening of Shipping, and diſcouragement of Mariners; the Walls of this Kingdome hereby deſerve alſo to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>Next then to his Majeſtyes loſs, is that of the Merchant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Cloathier; after which muſt follow detriment to all other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons depending on Trade, there being ſuch a Connexion of Trades one to another, and (the whole of Trade being enlarged by the abounding of Laborious People. Thoſe ſupply the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and Graziers with money, for you to ſupply the Gentry. They again ſcatter it amongſt the Tradeſmen, as may be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed by the building of the City of <hi>London,</hi> how Proviſion and all Conſumptive goods are advanced by it: by which circulation all degrees are either imployed, enriched, or both; and hence naturally comes Content, Harmony, and Pleaſure, one in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the Poor being by Imployment delivered from fear of want, the Gentry, Merchant, and Tradeſmen, by the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Trade therein. This Rationally is the ſtrength of any People, Poverty and Idleneſs brings their ſhame and Ruine, which would unavoidably follow want of Trade. And ſo much the more where the greateſt Trade hath been; if it fails, the greater Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty is and will be. And to inſtance, as here, in <hi>London,</hi> the Trade in Proviſion is the more, ſo by Conſequence it muſt be dear, and ſo beſt for all; ſo of the other hand, if the City ſhould be forced to keep ſo many thouſands, when all their work is done, as is now in the Building, it would be a great burden: ſo the caſe is in <hi>England</hi> in this particular, where great Trade have been formerly kept, and drawn ſeveral Families thither, and have raiſed Commodities there; but when it ſails, it is a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtate and condition thoſe places are in. To return, in ſhort
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98929:9"/>there is ſuch Connextion and dependency one upon another in <hi>England,</hi> that if one fail, all the reſt more or leſs, either more near, or remotely are concerned; as in the natural body; when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny member fails, the whole ſuffers thereby; and as all Trades and degrees of men may ſuffer by one miſtake in Trades, and in none more probably. I will ſay then this of Wool, as Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Artificers, Farmers, Sea-men, Fiſher-men, being the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which by their ſtudy and labour do principaly, if not only bring in, or give occaſion to the bringing in of wealth to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and other kind of people <hi>(viz.)</hi> Nobility, Gentry, Lawyers, Phyſicians, Schollars of all ſorts; Shop-keepers are they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from theſe, and diſtribute it again, and all are conſequently concerned in this rich Treaſure of Wool, becauſe this being a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture at home, ſets more hands at work than half the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>May I not with modeſty and within Compaſs, ſay three parts of Laborious and Induſtrious people? conſidering that moſt of the ſhipping is imployed in this affair, and alſo ſo many Trades that depend immediatly upon this of Cloathing, that moſt of other Trades are but for Proviſion, either in Food or Conveniencies for Cloathing: and ſo from his Majeſty to the meaneſt, all are more or leſs concerned, <hi>The King moſtly;</hi> not only in that his People are by that moſt imployed and provided for, nor in that ſuch a Staple Trade, the like whereunto the world hath not with good Advantage thereby is maintained; but becauſe ſo great a Revenue comes directly into him upon the Trade, occaſioned thereby: Thus as the King gains, or ſuffers moſt, ſo the perſons that have the greateſt Eſtates or Trades, and ſo all proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to the Beggar. And alſo conſidering that an accuſtomary thing begets ſuch an habit that is hard to reduce; as in our rough and undreſt Cloath to <hi>Holland,</hi> ſo it will be with all our Manufactures in <hi>France;</hi> nay I am informed that the <hi>French</hi> hath not only impoſed a great Tax upon our Woollen Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, from twenty to forty <hi>per cent,</hi> but have alſo (as is affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, beſide that their impoſition) abſolutely prohibited our Cloaths coming there. I am the more large in the demonſtration of this affair, not only becauſe this hath coſt me many years la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſtudy to conſult all ſorts of concerned perſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98929:10"/>mine own experience about it; nor becauſe it is ſo hard to convince people of the meanſt capacity, but ſome of the wiſer ſort, how to cure this diſmal malady: which ſome deſpairing of, have rather thoughts of ſetting up ſome other Manufacture in Lieu of endeavours to prevent the exportation of Wool and Manufactur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that at home, looking thereon as a thing not to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, (as that of Linnens in ſome capable parts of <hi>England</hi>) and a better improvement in the product of ſorrein plantations, which may alſo be ſet upon together herewith as an addition; ſo as ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſorts of perſons may be ſet better on work, not capable of this employment, and yet no prejudice to this of Cloathing: for all other Countryes have the advantage of <hi>England,</hi> or are equal to us in other Manufactures proper to their Countreys, but not in this of Cloathing: and it will be found that all Trades in <hi>England,</hi> wholly diſtinct from this of Cloathing, bring not the tythe of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that this doth.</p>
            <p>Since men cannot rationally believe the effects to be greater than the cauſe, the moſt of other Manufactures either is in being, or brought to uſe, by the Manufactures of Wool; even from the Farmer to the Merchant all are concerned in this of Wool, as may hereafter more appear. It now remains that we ſum up <hi>Englands</hi> loſs by the exportation of our Wool to Forrein Parts; not only in the advantage we might have by the Manufactureing thereof, here in <hi>England,</hi> as formerly noted; but alſo in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting af <hi>Dutch</hi> Cloath, and more in <hi>French</hi> Manufactures, becauſe <hi>England</hi> improves not their own Wools; and of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of <hi>Engliſh</hi> people, in putting ſuch a value upon <hi>French</hi> fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, when themſelves are in a better capacity, if improved, to produce the like, or better, and ſave the following ſums.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One Million of pounds <hi>Sterling</hi> yearly, in the Exportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Wool.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Five hundred thouſand pounds in rough Cloath, which is but half what Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> obſerves in his time.</p>
            <p n="3">3. One hundred thouſand pound yearly, in Importing <hi>French</hi> Manufactures ſuperfluous.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Many thouſand pounds in Importing <hi>Dutch</hi> Cloath.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And laſtly, the evil conſequences thereof in loſeing our Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, which would be encouraged thereby, &amp; are the ſtrength or
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98929:10"/>Walls of our Kingdome, as more particularly doth appear here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>Having now diſcovered the dammage, it is to <hi>England,</hi> in the Tranſportation of Wool from the King to the meaneſt, <hi>I</hi> ſhall endeavour alſo to diſcover the methods how it is done; and before I ſhall preſcribe Remedy (for it is not enough to know diſtempers, eſpecially ſuch that are ſo Conſumptive,) it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to know the cauſe of thoſe diſtempers; or elſe the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Remedies will in time come to be a diſeaſe, as it is too much in this caſe at this day in <hi>England:</hi> where the cauſes are miſtaken, the Remedies are conſequently miſapplyed, whereby a diſeaſe in ſuppoſition becomes one in <hi>effect;</hi> the methods or ways of this evil are—Firſt, in <hi>Rumny Marſh</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> where the greateſt part of rough Wooll is exported from <hi>England,</hi> put aboard French Shallops by night, ten or twenty men well armed to guard it; ſome other parts there are, as in <hi>Suſſex, Hampſhire,</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> the ſame methods may be uſed, but not ſo conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently. The ſame for coombed Wool from <hi>Canterbury,</hi> they will carry it ten or fifteen miles at night towards the Sea, with the like guard as before; but for other parts it muſt be done partly by the Remiſneſs of the Officers of his Majeſties Cuſtoms, and eaſie Compoſition for the forfeitures of the Bonds, as more ſhall appear anon.</p>
            <p>And then for coombed Wool in other parts, ſome is ſhipped off from <hi>London</hi> for Bales of Drapery; nay ſome at <hi>Lime,</hi> and alſo at <hi>Exon,</hi> where there is ten thouſand pounds Sterling weekly laid out in the woollen Manufactury, which is moſt for Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens wages: <hi>I</hi> know no place clear; and then another reaſon, why perſons are not detected, is, becauſe all the wools that have been taken in thoſe parts, where moſt hath been exported, have been ſuffered to go off at the ſame places after Judgments paſt, and by the Officers, to the ſame perſons at a low rate, being under rated to thoſe very men that intended to ſhip it at firſt: ſo that the evil is never like to be avoyded that way; only that which is taken, happily may be a little the dearer, to keep the Trade going; for I have enquired, and cannot underſtand, but of two parcels of wool that have been ſeaſed on in <hi>Kent,</hi> that have been uſed in <hi>England,</hi> but all ſent away, and ſo his Majeſties provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98929:11"/>is cheated, who keeps Servants at great wages to prevent ſuch abuſes.</p>
            <p>And then another cheat is under a pretenſe of wool from <hi>Hampton,</hi> to the Iſlands of <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Gernſey,</hi> &amp; ſometimes from other parts which is againſt the Law; for there is no wool to be exported to thoſe Iſlands, but only from <hi>Hampton,</hi> and that by Law ſhould be by weight: but now it goes by groſs, by the pack when it ſhould be weighed, but I believe not one pack in ten is weighed, for three packs is put into one. Then from <hi>Ireland,</hi> which is the greateſt miſchief of all to <hi>England,</hi> and much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed ſince the Act was in force againſt Cattel, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> wool can be ſold as cheap in <hi>France, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> as it is in thoſe places where wool is uſed in <hi>England,</hi> which is a great augmentation to us of prejudice for Foreiners to have our wool ſo cheap as we in <hi>England,</hi> having other conveniencies to underwork us as formerly hinted. The wayes there muſt be by the careleſsneſs of the Officers, in not taking ſolvant ſecurity and exactneſs in the weight of wool, and true examination of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of their Certificates, and partly by eaſie compoſitions, if not before bonds are forfeited, and happily much combed Wool there packt up as before, as bailes of Cloath, or barrels of Beef, and ſhiped as <hi>Iriſh</hi> Cloath; and in all points ſo cunningly carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as they are ſeldome diſcovered, and never ſealed as the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes in that caſe made and provided, do ſtrictly require.</p>
            <p>Here ſee what <hi>W. S.</hi> ſaith: <hi>Now to ſhew you more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe abuſes, how the Laws are croſſed and daily obſtructed to ſuch as endeavour to ſerve their Country, by ſuch as ought to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the proſecutors; ſure there will be very many practiſes of evil conſequents diſcovered; for firſt in the Cuſtom-Houſe, where bonds are taken, to the intent that theſe prohibited Commodities paſs not by means of Mariners out of the Nation, but only from Port to Port for accommodation of ſuch parts as want ſuch Commodities; they are very Remiſs and careleſs in taking of the Sea-mens diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their Obligatory Conditions; where alſo it is uſual with the Sea-men to bring fradulent Certificates, and ſo to cheat the Kings Providence, who keeps Servants at great wages purpoſely to prevent ſuch abuſes; or if there be a regular return of there Bonds,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98929:11"/>yet there is commonly a fraudulency in giving them, for the Maſters of ſhips will ſo continue their deſigne, as he who is Maſter at giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bonds,</hi> and is legally bound, ſhall immediatly paſs his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to another man, who taking charge of the Veſſel and Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, is notwithſtanding not engaged in the Poart Bond; and therefore, neither is he accomptable for breach of their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>again, when the Port bonds are juſtly taken, and as juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned; yet to prevent the true and real detection of the offender, and to diſhearten the legal proſecutor, ſome friends of the offender will clap an information againſt him, purpoſely to hinder and divert others, and ſoon after will let the Proſecution fall at his pleaſure; nay, it hath been ſaid, and peradventure not unjuſtly, that ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting informations have been amidated to the over-throw of the regal information; but when all is granted, and a full and formal hearing, and decree paſſed to the juſt condemnation of the offender: Yet when judgments and inquieries are granted, and do without er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the Clarks, (which is not always,) impower the Sheriffs and their Bayliffs to ſee Execution thereof made; it is familiar with thoſe Officers to return a</hi> non eſt inventus, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or a</hi> mortus eſt, viz. <hi>Not to be found, or dead, even then when the Offenders and the Officers have been known to be drinking together, at that very time when the</hi> Writ <hi>ſhould have been executed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>After all this, one ſtep farther will ſhew how charrety it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſeth Juſtice; for let all the former proceedings be granted, and be candid, and clear, and that the Law be indeed juſtly and legally executed; the offender in cuſtody, and nothing remaining; but that he honeſtly diſcharge hiasſelf with money, ſeeing Bail will not be admitted; nevertheleſs upon a lamentable Petition, and urging a great charge of Children to the Bench, the Offender is uſually ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to compound for Ten in the Hundred, or leſs, when by his offence he hath gained a Hundred for Ten, or more, and peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath undone a hundred Famelies or more in ſo doing: Yet all this while the honeſt Proſecutor, the only man that appears for the good of his Country, who ought by the Law to have the full benefit and advantage of the Law</hi> gratis, <hi>it being enough that he ſpend his time for the promotion of the publick Weal, after it hath coſt him ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98929:12"/>great ſums of money, &amp; large expenſe of time, to bring the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Tryal and Conviction, is diſmiſſed with little or no ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, unleſs he be rewarded with the brand of an informing Knave: Surely they who made theſe Lawes for the benefit of themſelves and their own Country, did intend a more current and juſt paſſage towards them, than thus to be obſtructed and baffeled. Such a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes as theſe made</hi> Theodoſius <hi>ſay as it is Recorded,</hi> that a wiſe man did himſelf injuſtice by hazarding his Wiſdome and Eſtate for the benefit of his Nation; <hi>and therefore ſome have not ſpared to urge that Cuſtoms and Impoſt, and Toles and Taxes might be taken away from honeſt laborious hazardous Trades and Adventurers, and be put upon litigious Suits at Law, and ſuch as make benefit of their corrupt breath, that is to ſay upon ſuch Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers as abuſe their Clyents, and ſuch malicious Clyents as abuſe the name of a juſt innocent Defendent. Nor is the Loſs in theſe by their Tranſportation all the injury, but when honeſt men well affected to the good of their Country, do detect theſe Caterpillers of the Common-wealth, who make ſo vaſt gain, as hath been denoted upon the materials ſo carefully prohibited, when they do endeavour by due courſe of Law to make ſtoppage thereof, and to have the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders puniſhed; ſo many are the evaſions, ſuch combinations and intereſt in the Officers, who ought to puniſh the Offenders; ſuch favour have they in Courts of Juſtice, and deceptions in the Return of Writs, and in general ſuch affronts and diſcouragements as the deareſt Lover of his Country, or moſt intruſted in Trade, dares not attempt to prevent that miſchief which his eyes behold to fall upon his Nation, or which his own perſon feels to pick his pocket.</hi> Thus far Mr. <hi>W. Smith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prevent all theſe inconveniences, it cannot be done without ſome alteration of ſome Laws, which is an Act of State; and I do preſume his Majeſty doth already, and the Parliament will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo conſider of it; as to accept of any helps that may be contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to them. In ſhort, I am of opinion, that if four things were done, there would be in a few moneths ſuch an alteration, which, if I ſhould now inſert, would be Incredible: yet I ſhall hint it; 1. To revive ſome former Act made in Parliament for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98929:12"/>a certain ſeaſon, as in the 4th. of <hi>Hen:</hi> 7. and revived thrice af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, which was done upon the ſame complaint, as now is; which if in force with ſome alteration, would be one ſtop: A ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is, for all perſons to be accomptable for their wool, becauſe there is time after it is bought to be wayed up, and ſetched away out of thoſe Countreys, where the danger is for to get acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for thoſe perſons, and to give ſecurity, as it is, from Port to Port, then being the ſame danger near the Sea. Thirdly, for <hi>Ireland,</hi> to have it confin'd to convenient Ports, both in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> And when all is done, there muſt be ſome perſons of known Integrity, and not mercenary men that muſt have the care and inſpection over all. Fourthly, In thoſe Countreys where no Cloathing is, it would be requiſite for a Store-houſe for ſmall parcels of Wool, and a Bond given that none be ſold to Fori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which is of ſo eminent advantage, as is by ſome ſaid to the <hi>Dutch, to be profit to the publick,</hi> Millions of pounds Sterling <hi>per annum;</hi> and to inſtance one caſe Sir <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Rawleigh</hi> accounts by this in his remains, <hi>page</hi> the 173, and 174. <hi>that in one year and half was drawn to the</hi> Hollanders, Hamburgers, <hi>and</hi> Embdenors, <hi>at the leaſt two Millions of pounds Sterling, from</hi> England <hi>for Corn, in a time of ſcarcity in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>And if a Bond is ſo advantageous for ſuch Commodities that are liable to he much impared in long lying; it's doubtleſs abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly more advantagous in ſuch a ſtable Commodity as wool is; and if practiſed would be of ſuch a uſe to <hi>England,</hi> that I think would enrich <hi>England</hi> more than I will now ſtand to account.</p>
            <p>I may add a fifth, which is, that there may be a ſhort and quick Tryal of Offenders, and that in ſuch place as the Offender may have leaſt oppertunity for Evaſions.</p>
            <p>We will conclude the whole with a ſhort ſurvey of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Immunities which Cloathing hath conferred, upon <hi>England</hi> with which the glory of it extends to the very utmoſt inhabited parts of the world, and without which, the Ark of Gods mercy, and the glory of this Land is like to depart.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98929:13"/>
            <p> Firſt, the reducing of Cloathing to <hi>England</hi> in Manufacture as well as in Materials (which muſt a thouſand times repeat <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> gratitude to the memory of that ever renowned King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Third) hath produced ſuch opulent and magnificent ſocieties of Merchants, as the whole world cannot again demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that is to ſay, firſt, the Merchant Adventurers Company, whoſe Governours, Preſident, Conſults, and the like chief Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers are not of leſs eſteem, where they pleaſe no ſeat themſelves, then are the Reſidentiaries of the greateſt Princes, and ſo much the more Cordial is their welcome, as each mans profit leads his affection beyond his Reverence to publick Embaſſies, becauſe Proximity to a mans perſonal intereſt ſits nearer in his thoughts then when he is involved in the publick concernment.</p>
            <p>This Company hath by their Policy and Order, ſupplanted thoſe ſocieties of the Hance Towns (as they are called) who vending an inconſiderable number of Cloaths, and at low rates, did never the leſſs account <hi>England</hi> obliged to them for their Markets and Shipping: Whereas at this day the Merchant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturer do utter ten times as many Cloaths Annually in the ſame Markets at far better prices; And in anſwer to the ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping which <hi>England</hi> had in thoſe times from thoſe Countreys at dear entertainment, this Trade of Cloathing, and this particular Company of Merchants, have furniſhed the Navy Royal from time to time, and upon all occaſions with ſuch ſtrengths as they have not feared, if they have not awed the greateſt Naval Forces ſayling upon the Ocean, he that may have the favour to peruſe their Records, ſhall find what oppertune Service they did for their Country in the year Eighty-Eight, and ſince upon all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary occaſions wherein this Nation hath been embroyled with any other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Next, the Eaſt-Land Company hath planted the Trade of Cloathing all about the Baltick Seas, which at this day imployes many Warlike Ships, and gives at great increaſe of Marriners to the no ſmall growth of <hi>Englands</hi> ſtrenth at Sea.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Muſcovia</hi> Company have diſcovered the paſſage by the North Cape, and the great Trade of <hi>Greenland,</hi> what wealth oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs to <hi>England</hi> by the <hi>Turky</hi> and <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, is not eaſie to be numbered; their ſhipping alſo being as ſtrong, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98929:13"/>rich as any that ſwim upon the Seas. How one of them hath by the trade of Cloathing only engroſſed all manner of wealth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the <hi>Levant Seas;</hi> And how the other of them hath eſtabliſhed the rich Trades of Silks, Spices, Jewels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the Southern parts of the world, is by all Admired, though by none to be valued, and what ſtrength of ſhipping theſe two Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes have produced, as they have been wonderful, ſo they have been formedable to all Nations: what Contribution the Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Trade with <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France</hi> hath given to <hi>Englands</hi> mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin power, is by thoſe Countrys themſelves feared, as well as by <hi>England</hi> found to its great ſecurity: And as theſe unvaluable bleſſings have befallen <hi>England</hi> by the Trade of Cloathing, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litickly and providently drawn into Societies, Companyes, and Corporations; ſo the looſe Tranſactions of Trade in other for the Countreys have rendered them ſo poor at Sea; as were it not ſhipping of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> the very life of Commerce would periſh, would return to the ſame Wilderneſs; &amp; uſeleſsneſs as it is now in <hi>Greenland</hi> and the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> where civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment hath not once been heard of.</p>
            <p>Again, If compariſon be made for richneſs of Trade between Cloathing and any, or all other ſubſtances of Merchandiſes, whereby any Nation, but more eſpecially <hi>England,</hi> may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched, neither the Silks nor Furs, nor Wines, nor Spices, nor Bullion it ſelf or all other Countreys can render that account of its own, or can in proportion equalize <hi>England,</hi> in Cloathing, Food, Shipping, Strength of people, and wealth of money.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98929:14"/>
            <head>About the Manufactureing of Wool.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THat this rich Treaſure in it ſelf, of far more worth than the Golden Mines of</hi> India <hi>to</hi> England, <hi>is ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, or adulterated in the Manufactureing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by many of the Manufactors, ſome of which wanting skill, others principles of honeſty, the Laws in that caſe being ſo much, neglected in</hi> England, <hi>and want of ſome new Laws for the new Drapers, hath occaſioned the woollen Manufacture to be rendered contemptible both at home and abroad, and ſo much the more, or the rather, becauſe the</hi> Dutch, Flemins, (<hi>and it is feared in time the</hi> French <hi>alſo</hi>) do by care and induſtry indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to excel our Engliſh; <hi>the conſequence is to looſe our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Trade, and this principally by a liberty taken, ſo that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and conſcientious perſons come to dammage by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers falſe way of gains, according to Mr.</hi> Childes <hi>third head in that of Trade, and Intereſt; that the Advantage the</hi> Dutch <hi>have of us in all their Native Commodities is their exactneſs, by which meanes their creat is ſo, that it is taken by its contents, (and ours not) which is very advantageous, which is done by the qualifications of thoſe perſons that have the overſight, and are intruſted in that affair, which is not done in</hi> England, <hi>but gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In general all States and Common-wealths are ſupported by two providential works <hi>(viz.)</hi> Reward and Puniſhment; for as no Law can compel men to be corporally laborious, or ſtudious in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; literature, unleſs rewards be annexed to all ſuch compulſion; ſo no providence can attend the preſervation of profitable deſignes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98929:14"/>either in Learning or Trade, unleſs ſuch puniſhments be enjoyned: This opinion that profound Senator <hi>Cicero</hi> alledgeth from <hi>Solon,</hi> one of the ſeven wiſe <hi>Graecians,</hi> and the only man of them which gave Lawes; and this is the weak and frail Eſtate of men and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that unleſs they be as well encouraged in their endeavours, as puniſhed in their miſdemeanors, they will ſpeedily become Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, and ruin all as is too too much feared in this caſe in <hi>England</hi> at this day; and as before about the Wool, ſo the working for the greateſt part hath been confined to <hi>England</hi> this three hundred years, and untill theſe late years has been ſo preſerved, by the diligence of ſuch Officers as have been ordained and impowered, carefully to ſee the Manufactures kept under thoſe rules which the Laws have provided for their perfection; and ſeeing this Nation is by God peculiariſed in theſe two bleſſings <hi>(viz.)</hi> Wools and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, and through the vigilancy of its Monarches ſafe guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Laws, that the native Manufactures might not be undermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the practices of Foreiners; their ancient providence exacts from the preſent age the ſame preſervation (as before in the Wool) that the Dutch do not undermine us out of all. Again, we may be taught by their diligence, who though they have few or no native Commodities, yet are rich and thriving; (and we who have all, are poor and decaying at leaſt the Country) who ſpare no attendance in overſeeing and ſearching the true makeing of their Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures as above, for their exactneſs, giving therefore power and Commiſſions to perſons of more than ordinary worth amongſt them (whom they call cure or care Maſters) to ſee every thing according to the Law; and wherever they find a defect, they make a default upon the Cloath, which firſt is recompenſed by a fine to the State for abuſing the Laws, and afterward remains to admoniſh the buyer, who thereby may guard his purſe; and in caſe the Cloathier be abuſed by any of his Work folks, he checks his dammage upon the true offender in his wages. Now in <hi>England</hi> there is ſo much the contrary, that many perſons take liberty for want of a regular or legal courſe followed, either for time or forme in working; there is not any of the Relations to Cloathing which doth obſerve ſuch an exact rule of Apprentiſhip (which is not the leaſt cauſe that the Manufactures of Wool are ſo abuſively and deceptiouſly made in <hi>England</hi>) notwithſtanding it is enjoyned in very ſtrict and penal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98929:15"/>manner by the Statute Lawes; the chief inconveniences of which, is, that the Trade ſo general in uſe, and maintenance of even num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs Families, doth by its own vaſt exorbancy convert into Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and ſo thoſe great multitudes of people become diſcredited, beggered, and finally ruined, to the deſtruction of themſelves and the Nation which gave them ſo great a Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Another prejudice and not the leaſt, is, that the Nation which hath given them being, and inveſted them with ſuch materials for Cloathing, is diſhonered by falſe and abuſive works: And it is not a little ſcandal to that Nation which God hath perticularly endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thoſe bleſſings which others want, when its people ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert thoſe good things which God hath beſtowed upon it to evil and deceptious practiſes; In this conſideration it is obſervable (by ſome) how little comparitively is the Drunkenneſs of thoſe Countrys which produce Wines, and wherein lies their perſonal riches, and their Nations Honour, though their other ſins may ſufficiently ſwell, their ultimate account; yet doubtleſs it ſtrengthens their laſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, in that they abuſe not that endowment which God hath made the original of their Being and Subſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Another conſideration is, the Cheat it puts upon all the world, for though every Country hath not the benefit of the Manufacture in themſelves, yet are there few of them condemned to ſuch igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as not to diſcern the Couzenage which falſe Cloathing puts upon them, in which caſe to the aforeſaid diſhoner they add a curſe, and it was a chief care in <hi>Jacobs</hi> practiſe for a Bleſſing, that he turned it not into a Curſe; how much more is this of conſideration, when the bleſſing comes by gift, and not by deſign or procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And further, great may be the thought of heart, when the ſins of falſe Lucre and Covetuouſneſs (which is Idolatry) are in full pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of ſuch as have the full plenty to make weight and meaſure, yet make it the Art of their practiſes as well as the practiſe of their Art, to Cozen both the wiſe and weak: It can be no great wonder, nor without abundance of preſidents, if God for ſins of ſuch wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs remove his bleſſings, (with which this Nation is peculiarly enriched and dignified,) and give them to a people which will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him a better, more juſt, and more profitable account of his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; and its no news, that though <hi>England</hi> be by the Almighty,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98929:15"/>chiefly ordained to produce the Materials, yet the Manufactures be given to a people, which will render him a better Account; all this and much more is expected, if the Native people continue to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the Native Commodity, as of neceſſity they muſt, when they know not how to uſe it. The wiſdome of our Anceſtors hath been liberally manifeſted in this particular. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors be conſtantly made Apprentices for ſeaven years at leaſt, the contrary is one great reaſon, that by ignorance ſo many abuſes are, that are unremidable: Another reaſon, why Apprentices are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally confined to ſeaven years ſervitude, is to the end, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors (in each Art) multiply not beyond the ſupport of their Trade, which were not to increaſe good Subjects, but Vagabonds, which doubtleſs was not the intention of King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> (ever to be remembered by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, when in his deſign in bringing Cloathing to <hi>England,</hi> a chief part was to multiplie his people, as by his Native and Alleageant Subjects (ſuch as by and by you will underſtand) he might ſecurely poſſeſs the Conqueſts wherewith God had bleſſed him, which were beyond any Chriſtian Prince's in his time. It is utterly againſt reaſon that a Nation can be poor, whoſe people are numerous, if their Induſtry be compelled and incouraged, and their Idleneſs be puniſhed and reformed. It is the opinion of ſome, that it's not the barrenneſs of a Countrey which can forbid this Maxim. The <hi>Scots</hi> are an abounding and numerous people, and they have a ſoyle which to a Traveller eye, ſeems to produce nothing towards a ſo vaſt maintenance of the body of that people; yet are they in all parts of the world a warlike and honoured Nation, helpful to all Princes in their Wars, and ready upon occaſion to return to the Aſſiſtance of their Brethren, be their caſe good or bad. The Dutch are a numerous Nation, daily mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying in a Country which hath in compariſon nothing of its own growth to ſupport them, either in Food or Cloathing, yet they want nothing neither in neceſſaries or wealth, becauſe they are induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. What Crick of the Seas do they leave unviſited? and in ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping are ſo ſtored as moſt parts of the world do love or fear them. Now a great increaſe (at leaſt) of good people (as above hinted in King <hi>Edward</hi>) reſts upon the regulation of Trade; for its not the number of workmen, but number of good workmen which increaſeth Families, and it's Families which increaſeth and ſpreadeth good
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98929:16"/>people; the other for want of knowledg and skill, being fixed no where, becauſe their labours will not maintain themſelves, much<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Families: For who will uſe a workman, who hath neither skill nor credit, when he can imploy one that hath both?</p>
            <p>Of principle importance therefore is the Regulation of Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhips, both to the beſt increaſe of people, and to the honeſt, credita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and wealthy Manufactures of Wool, and eſpecially of Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (being the Antient'ſt Manufacture) for want of which not only the former denoted faults are daily found in their works, but good work-men are underſold and ruined <hi>(as formerly hinted)</hi> by bad, and the whole Nation involved in great diſhonour, as after you will hear.</p>
            <p>Now Juſtice, which all men cry up, and few practiſe, is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue both divine and humane; Divine Juſtice is either from God to man, wherein his Providence is his Juſtice, by which he governeth the world, or it is from man towards God, and then its piety, whereby he returns to God prayſe and glory for his numberleſs bleſſings in Republicks, Cityes and Towns, its Equity, the fruit whereof is Peace &amp; Plenty; in domeſtick relations between Man &amp; Wife, it's <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Concord; from Servants to Maſters, good Will and Diligence; from Maſters to Servants, its Humanity and Gentleneſs; and from a man to his own body, health and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. There is none of all theſe Relations but is neceſſary and important to the Reformations in the abuſes, defaults, deceptions, and grievances committed upon Cloathing, which in this diſcourſe have in ſome meaſure been diſcovered, and by which both God and man are juſtly provoked.</p>
            <p>The Juſtice we are to uſe to relieve the complaints before exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, is either diſtributive, or Commutative; Juſtice diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, is to give each man his deſerts, whether it be honour or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And Commutative Juſtice, is in bargaining, bartering, exchanging, or in any tranſactions between man and man, to uſe all means to keep Promiſes, Covenants and Contracts; and for a man to be have himſelf as he would have others do to him, to receive the Innocent into protection, to repreſs and puniſh offenders, without which, common intercourſe and humane ſociety muſt neceſſarily be diſſolved; and for preſervation whereof, I have read, that in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient times, the Fathers have not ſpared their own Sons.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98929:16"/>
            <p> The <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Kings, to whom Antiquity gives the priviledg of makeing Laws, the <hi>Graecians,</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> deified Juſtice, and would not violate it towards their Enemies; ſo juſt alſo were the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> and ſo free from diſtruſting each other, as even for the publick ſafety, they uſed neither Locks nor Barrs, inſomuch that one asking <hi>Archidamus,</hi> who thoſe Governours were, which ſo juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, happily, and gloriouſly governed the Common-wealth of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemon:</hi> he anſwered, that they were firſt the Laws, &amp; afterwards the Magiſtrates executing thoſe Lawes: for Law is the rule of Juſtice, and Juſtice the end of the Law, which indeed is the Life of all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ready way to rectifie abuſes about Cloathing, were to compare them with the rules of the Law provided for them, for which there is Law, (and new Laws where they are wanting) nevertheleſs holds not in all points. For inſtance, the Law em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powers the Merchants and Drapers to be their own Searchers, and to puniſh the Cloathiers Purſe, as they find his works to be faulty; and ſo they do, to the no ſmall grief of the Cloathier: but the Retayling-Buyer is not hereby at all relieved; the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſelling to him theſe faults, for which he was before paid by the Cloathier; the Merchants do the ſame, by cauſing their Cloathiers to bring their Manufactures into the Merchants pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Ware-Houſes, where their own Servants are Judges, who upon ſearching the Cloath, do make, and marke faults enough, for which they have reparable abatements; but themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain do practiſe all fraudulent wayes they can to barter and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change thoſe faults away, without giving any allowance for them. I ſpeak not of all but ſome; and though ſometimes they be detected, yet find they means to ſave their purſes, whilſt their Nation ſuffers in honour, and the Laws are vilified to Foreiners, who ſtain the Juſtice of the Nation with weakneſs and fraud. True it is, that in the</hi> Netherlands, where their cunning is as piercing, as their practice is common, they (even every buyer) do ſearch with diligence, and make themſelves reparations, firſt to the Merchants great loſs, and ſo in courſe to the Cloathiers no ſmall dammage: But in all this, the State remains much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by the ſcandal, and rob'd of thoſe Fines which the Lawes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98929:17"/>in punniſhment, do give to the publick Revenue, which if they were rightly and legally attended, would render a vaſt gain to the Common-wealth by a general Reformation.</p>
            <p>Now in finding out the cauſes why Manufacture in Cloathing becomes ſo abuſed, there may be good uſe of the Drapers and Merchants knowledg and skill; yet the application of the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is a work of State and Policy, in making and executing the Laws proportionable to the grievance, in which inſtance it doth not hold; for though the Merchants and Drapers be able Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the abuſes, yet they are not competent reformers of the grievances, becauſe they are intereſted in participating of thoſe gaines which the faults occaſion and intend. Therefore it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that both Cloathiers, Merchants, and Drapers, may be joyned by the Magiſtrates approbation,</p>
            <p>Nor is this all the abuſe; for in ſuch parts of the world as the Buyers are not in ability of knowledg, like the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who make Cloaths themſelves, and eſpecially in thoſe parts where the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in Religion is ſo great, as it is between Chriſtians and Turks, there the corrupt Merchant cauſeth the Name of God to be Blaſphemed: for when thoſe people; (whoſe eye and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment gives them not ſo good information as doth their proof and wearing) do find themſelves cheated in their Garments, they preſently conclude that there is no fear of God in that place, nor obedience to their Rulers, for Conſcience, which muſt aſſuredly procure much ſcandal to Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>It hath been noted that the original of money, was from ſheep, affirming that the Antient Signature upon money, was a Sheep; and its further obſerved, that Mercandizes were the cauſe of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; and there being no greater Merchandize than are from the Sheep, it is evident, that there is nothing more requiſite to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the enriching this Nation (whoſe peculiar bleſſing reſts in Sheep) than ſtrictly to hold the Manufactures to the letter and rule provided for their juſt making; and that the Laws be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially executed; and it being apparent that this Nation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be rich without a conſtant utterance of Cloathing, nor can that be done without a perfect reformation in the particulars of the works.</p>
            <p>It doth undeniably follow, that Cloathing muſt be purged
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98929:17"/>from its Corruption, or <hi>England</hi> muſt be poor. It is therefore the Manufactors which abuſe the Wool, and thereby impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently give advantage to the <hi>Dutch:</hi> whereas a perfection in the making of Cloaths in <hi>England,</hi> will capacitate the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to underſel the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for a true Reformation and Regulation of thoſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages that have befallen <hi>England,</hi> by the falſe and deceptions Manufacturing of Wools, and to bring the Trade to its primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive worth; we muſt rightly underſtand the cauſe of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, or elſe we can never preſcribe ſuitable remedies as before, but the contrary; the ſuppoſed remedy will be worſe that the diſeaſe. The principle or grand cauſe of all our miſery, in all theſe things formerly ſpoken to both in Tranſportation of Wool, and the bad Manufacturing thereof, is by that diviſion in Trade, both in Merchant and Cloathier, by which meanes it falls out that by the conſequence of one mans ſingle Act, a thouſand per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be undone; this I have obſerved in ſeveral perſons in this Kingdome, and I know no way ſo profitable to prevent (at leaſt ſome of that miſchief) as by incorporating the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, and faithfulneſs therein; as witneſs <hi>Norwich,</hi> and <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter;</hi> the miſery is the liberty, taken in that which is of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity a Union, as before by a Law, and more liberty by a Law for ſome in matters of Conſcience, for compulſion can never make that unity as the Law of that Relation doth require, in this as in all others things, <hi>to do to others, as we would have others do unto us,</hi> which is the Royal Law of Heaven) The great and main inducement to theſe two things, as good reaſon (if we will have Trade) to obſerve the <hi>Dutch</hi> in both theſe things, as not the leaſt cauſe of their riches, (having nothing of their own growth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively with <hi>England,</hi>) yet are a Rich people, and much by our Commodities, whilſt we are diſputing whether it be good for us: And I cannot paſs by what I have heard of the Follies of the <hi>Indians,</hi> that will part with a rich Treaſure for a Trifle; ſo we are to the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> by their policies and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting practices, which draw from us, and ſtill covet to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſt the Wealth and Coyne of this Kingdome, and ſo with one Commodity (as formerly the Wool) to weaken us, and finally
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98929:18"/>beat us out of our Trades in other Countreys, and thus they do (eſpecially the <hi>Dutch</hi>) more fully obtain their purpoſes by their convenient priviledges, and ſettled conſtitutions, by which they draw multitudes of Merchants to Trade with them, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations to inhabit amongſt them, which makes them popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and there they make Store-Houſes of all Forein Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, wherewith upon every occaſion of Scarcity and Dearth, they are able to furniſh Foreiners with plenty of thoſe Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, which before in time of plenty they Engroſſed &amp; brought home from the ſame places; which doth greatly augment Power and Treaſure to their Stocks, beſides the Common Good in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Poor on work, as in ſeveral particulars mentioned by Mr. <hi>Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>By having in their greateſt Councils of State and Warr, Tradeing Merchants that have lived abroad in moſt parts of the world, who have not only the Theoretical knowledg, but the Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Experience of Trade; sby whom Laws &amp; Orders are contrived, and Peace with Forein Princes projected, to the great advantage of their Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Their Law of</hi> Gavel-kind, <hi>whereby all their Children poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs an equal ſhare of their Fathers Eſtates after their Deceaſe, and ſo are not left to wraſtle with the World in their Youth, with inconſiderable aſſiſtance of Fortune, as moſt of our youngeſt Sons of Gentlemen in</hi> England <hi>are, who are bound Apprentices to Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Their exact making of all their Native Commodities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Their giving great encouragement and immunities to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventors of new Manufactures, and the diſcoverers of any new Myſteries in Trade, and to thoſe that ſhall bring the Commodities of other Nations firſt in uſe and practice amongſt them, for which the Author never goes without his due reward allowed him at the publick charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Their contriving and building of great Ships to ſayle with ſmall charge, not above one third of what we are at for Ships of the ſame burthen in</hi> England. <hi>And compelling their ſaid Ships (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſmall force) to ſayle alwayes in Fleets, to which in all time of danger they allow a Convoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98929:18"/> 6. <hi>Their parcimonious and thrifty living, which is ſo extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, that a Merchant of one hundred thouſand pound Eſtate with them, will ſcarce ſpend ſo much</hi> per annum, <hi>as one of fifteen hundred pounds Eſtate in</hi> London.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>The Education of their Children, as well Daughters as Sons, all which, be they of never ſo great quality or Eſtate, they always take care to bring up to write perfect good hands, and to have the full knowledge and uſe of Arithmetick and Merchants Accounts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>The lowneſs of their Cuſtoms, and the height of their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe: which is certainly the moſt equal and indifferent Tax in the world, and leaſt prejudicial to any people, as might be made appear, were it the ſubject of this diſcourſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>The careful providing for, and imployment of their poor: which it is eaſie to demonſtrate, can never be done in</hi> England <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritively to what it is with them, while it's left to the care of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Pariſh to look after their own only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Their uſe of Banks, which are of ſo immenſe advantage to them, that ſome, (not without good grounds,) have eſtimated the profit of them to the publick, to amount to, at leaſt one Million of pounds Sterling,</hi> per annum.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Their toleration of different opinions in matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by reaſon whereof, many induſtrious people of other Countreys, that diſſent from the eſtabliſhed Government of their own Churches, reſort to them with their Families and Eſtates, and after a few years co-habitation with them, become of the ſame Common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Their Law-Merchants, by which all controverſies between Merchants and Tradeſmen are decided in three or four dayes time, and that not at the fortieth part (I might ſay in many caſes not the hundreth part) of the Charge they are with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>The Law that is in uſe among them for Transference of Bills for debt from one man to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>Their keeping up publick Regiſters of all Land, and Houſes Sold or Mortgaged; whereby many chargeable Law-Suits are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and the ſecurities of Lands and Houſes rendered indeed, ſuch as we commonly call them Real Securities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>The lowneſs of Intereſt of money with them, which in peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able times exceeds not three</hi> per cent. per annum.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98929:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>To Conclude with a ſhort Survey of thoſe things in General, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my time will not permit to enlarge upon it particularly (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my purpoſe) nor ſo to Correct the former Papers for want of time, being expoſed to much Travel, I muſt humbly beg the Reapers pardon for ſome Errors paſſing the Preſs in my abſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt thing obſerved in the <hi>Dutch,</hi> is to have experienc'd perſons in all Councels skil'd, as Wel Practical, as Theoretical knowledge, which is without all peradventure of ſuch advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that nothing but experience of it can put the value.</p>
            <p>The ſecond I ſhall not touch.</p>
            <p>The third I have at large to eated <hi>(viz.)</hi> of the advantage in exactneſs in all Commodities, of which we have ſufficient expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience at home as well as abroad, that one and the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity for goodneſs, yet if one have the reputation more than the other, it ſhall not only have a quick Market, but ſhall yield 10 or 15 <hi>per cent,</hi> more than the other. I ſpeak this of what is matter of Fact in the woollen Manufacture in my own knowledge</p>
            <p>The fourth is the Incouragement to thoſe that are any way beneficial to the Publick, which is contrary in <hi>England</hi> to its ſhame, as well as to its apparent Loſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hence it is that thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are imployed in publick affairs, that have not principles of honeſty, are liable to thoſe temptations of Bribery and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, being beyond my ſpeare.</p>
            <p>Time permits me not to make any further recapitulation. But for my Language in the whole, the Ingenuous peruſer will, I truſt, rather value my ſerious Intentions (while I write to matter of Controverſy, but what may redound to the Honour and Advantage of his Majeſty and Kingdoms) than criticize upon my defect of Scholaſtick phraſe, or Logical method; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never enriched with opportunities of education thereto, yet have ſo much of a Chriſtian and true Engliſh-man, as to wiſh every Reader Happineſs both here and hereafter.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 2, <hi>l,</hi> 15, for Land <hi>r,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, p, 5, <hi>l,</hi> 27, for is <hi>r,</hi> by; <hi>p,</hi> 10, <hi>l,</hi> 16, inſert Advantage of a; p, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>r,</hi> 18, for you <hi>r,</hi> them; <hi>p,</hi> 19, <hi>l.</hi> 15 for Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l <hi>r,</hi> real; <hi>l,</hi> 28, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſelf himſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>p,</hi> 21, <hi>l,</hi> 8, for then <hi>r,</hi> there; <hi>l,</hi> 15, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d he gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>r,</hi> Bank; <hi>l,</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; for, Bond <hi>r,</hi> Bank; <hi>p,</hi> 24, <hi>l,</hi> 7, for D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>apers <hi>r,</hi> Draperles; <hi>p,</hi> 25, <hi>l,</hi> 15, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures <hi>r,</hi> Manufactors.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
